A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Africa and Middle East Program, Regional Director, Office Files of Timothy Bork FA700
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Africa and Middle East Program, Regional Director, Office Files of Timothy Bork
1986-1996
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA700
10.8 Cubic Feet
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Arrangement
The Africa and Middle East Program Office Files of Timothy Bork are divided into the following nine boxes:
1. Memos, Strategy Papers and Reports, 1994-1996 2. Subject Files, 1991-1995 3. Subject Files, 1957-1994 (bulk 1988-1994) 4. People Files, Subject Files, 1994-1996 5. Meeting Files, Organization Files A-B 6. Organizations Files C-M 7. Subject Files, N-Z; A-J 8. Program Reviews and Subject Files, 1986-1993 9. Operations Files
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement
As received.
Scope and Contents
Contains subject files, organizational files, program planning and reviews, operations files, and strategy papers and reports.
Biographical / Historical
Segment One: International Activities of the Ford Foundation: An Overview
The Foundation's aspiration to become a national and international philanthropy for the advancement of human welfare was first formally expressed in the seminal 1949 report of the Gaither Study Committee, Report of the Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program (RAC Library, call letters 361.7 GAI ), which was commissioned by the Board of Trustees to chart the Foundation's future. Foundation Trustees launched Ford's international grantmaking activities in 1950 when they approved the committee's report and its embrace of peace, democracy, and freedom. Since then, the Foundation has tackled these goals using a variety of strategies and responding to changing contexts, from the Cold War to the 1989 fall of the Berlin Wall and beyond.
Toward the Foundation's aspirational goal, "the establishment of peace", its international activities have comprised a wide range of conceptual approaches and focus areas. These include international affairs, international studies, international understanding, arms control and disarmament, international law, international economic concerns, and overseas development in nearly every region of the world. Three distinct periods emerge for the international grantmaking defined by external contextual changes and internal changes in Foundation leadership and structures: the expansion era of 1950-1965; the transition and restructuring years of 1966-1988; and the post-1989 shift away from Cold War dichotomies. During each of the distinct historical periods the consistent objectives were: 1) to ensure freedom and democracy in developed countries; 2) to foster education and international understanding in all countries; and 3) to contribute to the social, economic, and political development of less developed countries.
Biographical / Historical
Segment 4. Period Sketch - The Post-1989 Shift Away from Cold War Dichotomies
Between 1989 and 1991, dramatic changes in the external international conditions created a significantly different context for Ford Foundation's international activities both in the United States and overseas. In November, 1989, the Berlin Wall fell. In February 1990, in South Africa, Nelson Mandela was released from prison. In December 1991, the Soviet Union dissolved. As a consequence, the Cold War was over, Western Europe no longer had a special strategic role in the Foundation, and program-related activities in Eastern Europe and the former Soviet Union multiplied. The Foundation not only continued the earlier efforts to fund leadership in the region; from 1990-1994, Ford also spent $1 million on the training of newly-elected parliamentarians in Eastern Europe and the former USSR. By 1993, half of the funds for grantmaking related to the former Soviet bloc were going to in-country individuals and institutions.
In 1989, Thomas also instituted a major restructuring of the Foundation to fulfill his vision of "One Foundation." All programs were put into one division led by Vice President Susan Berresford. Carmichael joined the Institute of International Education to run a program on Soviet and Eastern European Affairs and then higher education in South Africa. All the Foundation grant programs - domestic and international - reported to Berresford: Africa and the Middle East (AME, formerly MEA), Asia (ASIA), Latin American and the Caribbean (LAC/OLAC), Human Rights and Governance (HRG), Education and Culture (EC), Program-Related Investments (PRI), and International Affairs (IA).
The change in South Africa opened up many new opportunities to work in partnership with a range of South Africa partners to promote and sustain the transition to democracy. The Foundation supported women's groups working on law, development and reproductive rights. It contributed, for example, to the groups working on the Women's Chatter in South Africa, resulting in the adoption in 1994 of the first constitution anywhere that specifically included sections on women's rights.
During the 1990s, the promising political changes in African countries and elsewhere provided a positive perspective to counteract the continuing economic constraints facing the Foundation and the rising debt in developing countries. Both to reinforce local democratic initiatives and to address its economic challenges, the Foundation's field offices across Africa and the developing world shifted their support toward the promotion of smaller scale community-based initiatives.
Thomas supported work on arts and culture, not as a goal in itself, but, instead, as a means for promoting social justice, education, and human rights, both in the United States and in developing countries. At the same time, while reducing support for cultural institutions in the United States, such institutions received support overseas to preserve and celebrate national and local cultural heritages. While in South Africa, for example, the Foundation provided support for Johannesburg anti-apartheid theatre groups, in West Africa it funded for nearly two decades a program to preserve and make accessible cultural heritage by expand the training of museum leaders and strengthening museum exhibit and outreach capabilities.
In the early 1990s, the Foundation through its India office helped establish an independent foundation to enhance sustainability in the arts community. Ford envisioned new opportunities for cultural institution to rely on local resources focus on new forms of creativity and encourage young artists, in particular. Similar to the Indian effort, the Ford office in Egypt in 1993 provided support for an arts-focused foundation.
When Susan Berresford became president in 1996, with a strong commitment to globalization as well as concern for the uncertainty it created, she reorganized the Foundation in to three large program themes that would inform grantmaking in the United States and developing countries: Assets with a focus on poverty, Peace and Social Justice on rights issues, and Education, Media, Arts and Culture to pull together related endeavors. She also created a separate communications program. Each program was led by a vice president. Berresford strongly reinforced the institutional and grantmaking goal of affirmative action, an organizational goal that had been initiated in the Bundy era.
She maintained significant support, domestically and internationally for women's issues. She endorsed and encouraged the worldwide meetings staff members and grantees to continue to hold joint meetings in order to create a greater sense of partnership and shared purpose. The more promising international situation enabled the Ford Foundation in 1996 to open an office in Russia (Moscow) and in Vietnam (Hanoi). Berresford encouraged the development of local and regional peace and security programs in developing countries. A regional security, peace, and cooperation program in India, for instance, focused on the work of civil society groups as an increasingly prominent regional interest in South Asia.
In this period, the Foundation gave renewed the prominence of arts and culture in the US and maintained the commitment in developing countries. By 2000, funding levels for the Education, Media, Arts and Culture division were approaching parity with the other two, Assets and Peace and Justice.
Berresford also encouraged each of the programs to hold worldwide meeting to promote cross-program and cross-national collaboration in fields such as human rights, income generation, cultural preservation, and building capacity in the arts and arts management. One persistent question of such initiatives. Toward that end, and building on the earlier experiences in India and Egypt, Berresford worked closely with her senior vice president, Barry Gaberman and other staff to establish new foundations at the local and national levels, particularly in developing countries. Gaberman had been at the foundation since 1973, starting as assistant to the representative in Indonesia. After serving in a number of different positions, by 1984, under Thomas, he served as deputy vice president in the U.S. and International Affairs program. After the 1989, Thomas and Berresford appointed him deputy vice president. 1996, Berresford appointed him senior vice president.
As the twentieth century came to a close, the economic conditions of the 1970s and 1980s that had resulted in so much global debt, with special impact on the developing world, were slowly turning around. Many countries were experiencing economic growth and burgeoning democratic initiatives. Not only was the global economic situation improving but the Foundation's assets were also growing. Consequently, the Foundation was in a strong position to bring attention to long-standing issues holding back developing countries. The grants programs addressed the pressing need both for advanced training of young- to mid-career adults living in marginalized and disadvantaged conditions along the equally, and for strengthening and building sustainability of universities across sub-Saharan Africa, along with enhancing broadband access for improved internet communications, promoting women in higher education, and strengthening postgraduate education.
Reacting to the tragedy of September 11, 2001, the Foundation provided immediate relief to affected local institutions in the United States. The Foundation also helped launch support a fund at the Institute of International Education to support scholars at risk in countries in conflict and under terrorist threats, especially in, but not limited to, the Middle East.
Biographical / Historical
Segment 4. Period Summary - The Post-1989 Shift Away from Cold War Dichotomies
Franklin Thomas's presidency, lasting until his retirement in 1995, was defined by a commitment to connect the Foundation's US and international activities around a few key themes. These themes were addressed through grants that created private sector partnerships, enhanced support for local community groups, and enlarged initiatives to promote human rights, with special attention to women's rights. Throughout Thomas's tenure, Ford staff reinforced his special commitment to bolstering marginalized communities and broadening access to the law and educational opportunity. The Ford Foundation led the way in building the fields of international security studies, arms control, human rights, and governance. Moreover, in this period, Ford was innovative in drawing together the fields of international cooperation and human rights into one program.
Susan Berresford in her tenure as president from 1996-1997 continued and expanded the activities she helped initiate under Thomas. She and her colleagues increased support for the arts and established a variety of major international collaborative efforts implementing the concept of one foundation. Ford staff in this period drew on the Foundation's time-tested grantmaking strategies (supporting individuals and new institutions as needed), while concentrating on under-addressed issues and underserved populations. With Berresford's encouragement, Foundation staff explicitly took into account the new global context, increasing opportunities for inclusion of disadvantaged populations in all of their activities.
- Memos, Strategy Papers and Reports, 1994-1996
  - Women and political liberalization: (a) Memo from A. Wadia to Tim Bork and others entitled, "Proposed Consultancy on Women and political liberalization in Africa and the Middle East, (b) Draft of above paper (Box 1 (SK#38713), Folder 1)
  - Strategy paper on building the Institutional capacities of const. Building for Africa Grantees, 1996 August (Box 1 (SK#38713), Folder 2)
  - AME Draft Paper on Media Development in Africa (Scope of work, memos included), 1995 September (Box 1 (SK#38713), Folder 3)
  - Bork's Speeches - Board of Trustees Speech from 3/96 meeting, 1996 March (Box 1 (SK#38713), Folder 4)
  - Proposed Study Commission of Nigeria (Meeting & Summaries) (Box 1 (SK#38713), Folder 5)
  - African Studies - Misc.: Memos, reports related to FF Initiative (Box 1 (SK#38713), Folder 6)
  - Africa & Middle East Program Review Meeting, 1995 March (Box 1 (SK#38713), Folder 7)
  - Scope of work and memos on AME Consultancy on Higher Education in Africa (Marcum Report), 1994-1995 (Box 1 (SK#38713), Folder 8)
  - Papers relating to U.S. National Summit on Africa - FF Internal discussion, 1995 May - 1996 January (Box 1 (SK#38713), Folder 9)
  - Summary of AME work in Higher Education in Africa by Ashton, 1993 (Box 1 (SK#38713), Folder 10)
  - Summary of Culture Programming in Africa and Middle East (Box 1 (SK#38713), Folder 11)
  - AME Program Strategy Paper - Improving the US Policy Environment for Africa's Renewed Development, 1996 September (Box 1 (SK#38713), Folder 12)
  - Hopes on the Horizon (notes, memos), 1995 April - 1996 March (Box 1 (SK#38713), Folder 13)
  - Hopes on the Horizon (notes, memos), 1994 December - 1995 July (Box 1 (SK#38713), Folder 14)
  - Hopes on the Horizon (notes, memos), 1994 April - December (Box 1 (SK#38713), Folder 15)
  - Hopes on the Horizon - multimedia documentary on Africa's Social History, Development (Box 1 (SK#38713), Folder 16)
  - AME Program Strategy Paper, memos & notes from the field (Box 1 (SK#38713), Folder 17)
  - Africa and Middle East Program Strategy Paper, 1995 (Box 1 (SK#38713), Folder 18)
  - Final Report: A Review of Public Education and constituency, 1993 (Box 1 (SK#38713), Folder 19)
  - Memos/Minutes of Post Review & comments on drafts (Box 1 (SK#38713), Folder 20)
  - Review of Constituency Builders, memos & minutes preview (Box 1 (SK#38713), Folder 21)
  - Agreement with Carnegie (Review) (Box 1 (SK#38713), Folder 22)
  - FF/CC Comments on draft review (Box 1 (SK#38713), Folder 23)
  - Terms of Reference (Box 1 (SK#38713), Folder 24)
  - Letters to Grantees about 1993 Review of AME/IA Constituency Groups for Africa (Box 1 (SK#38713), Folder 25)
  - Development Education Paper by Chris Allen (Box 1 (SK#38713), Folder 26)
  - Report: African Affairs Institutions in the U.S., part I by R. Simms Hamilton and T. Hodges submitted to the FF, 1994 January (Box 1 (SK#38713), Folder 27)
- Subject Files, 1991-1995
  - Cairo (Box 2 (SK#38715), Folder 1)
  - Lead Poisoning (Box 2 (SK#38715), Folder 2)
  - Cairo Apartment (Box 2 (SK#38715), Folder 3)
  - MENA Program (Box 2 (SK#38715), Folder 4)
  - Middle East Events (Box 2 (SK#38715), Folder 5)
  - Israel Program (Box 2 (SK#38715), Folder 6)
  - Lagos (Box 2 (SK#38715), Folder 7)
  - Nigeria Office Relocation (Box 2 (SK#38715), Folder 8)
  - Nigeria Country Agreement (Box 2 (SK#38715), Folder 9)
  - McHenry Trip (Box 2 (SK#38715), Folder 10)
  - General Obasanjo (Box 2 (SK#38715), Folder 11)
  - Dakar (Box 2 (SK#38715), Folder 12)
  - Senegal Closure (Box 2 (SK#38715), Folder 13)
  - FF/Sudan Agreement (Box 2 (SK#38715), Folder 14)
  - Khartoum, 1992-1995 (Box 2 (SK#38715), Folder 15)
  - Khartoum, 1991 (Box 2 (SK#38715), Folder 16)
- Subject Files, 1957-1994; 1988-1994
  - Quarterly Budget Projections FY 1993 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 1)
  - Budget Projections, 1993 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 2)
  - Carnegie Corporation, 1991 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 3)
  - Carter Center, 1991 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 4)
  - Democratization in Africa, 1990 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 5)
  - Florence Eid Report, 1992 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 6)
  - Environment, 1992 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 7)
  - Ethnic Conflict, 1992 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 8)
  - Report on Higher Education, 1991 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 9)
  - Donors for African Education (DAE): Maputo, Mozambique; Nairobi, Kenya, 1992 November 3 - 4 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 10)
  - Feb. 10-12, 1992; Manchester, England Oct. 28 – Nov. 1, 1991, 1991-1992 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 11)
  - Working Group on Higher Education: Dakar, 1991 June 26 - 27 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 12)
  - Higher Education Meeting - Harare, 1991 May 16 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 13)
  - Working Group on Higher Education: Accra, 1990 December 13 - 14 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 14)
  - Higher Education in South Africa Meeting, 1990 August 27 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 15)
  - Namibia Commission on Higher Education, 1990 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 16)
  - Mellon Foundation - Higher Education & Self-Help, 1993 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 17)
  - Middle East, 1992 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 18)
  - Mission of Africa, 1957 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 19)
  - Namibia Task Force, 1992 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 20)
  - Namibia, 1989–1992 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 21)
  - U. of Namibia Fund Proposal, 1993 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 22)
  - General Background U. of Namibia, 1993-1994 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 23)
  - Namibia President's Visit, 1993 June (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 24)
  - Namibia - Foundation Program Background, 1994 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 25)
  - Olusegun Obasanjo, 1988-1989 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 26)
  - New Staff Orientation, 1990 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 27)
  - Program Budget, 1992 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 28)
  - Orientation, 1991 September 16 - 23 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 29)
  - Orientation, 1992 September 14 - 25 (Box 3 (SK#38716), Folder 30)
- People Files, Subject Files, 1994-1996
  - Melanie Bixby, U.S. State Department (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 1)
  - Lynn Ellsworth, consultant (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 2)
  - Derk Hanekom, Minister of Land Affairs, South Africa (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 3)
  - Joun Hardbottle (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 4)
  - Mary King, President, Global Action Inc. (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 5)
  - Nelson Mandela, Address by (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 6)
  - Marguerite Michaels, Fellow at Council on Foreign Relations (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 7)
  - African Studies Initiative (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 8)
  - Agriculture (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 9)
  - AIDS (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 10)
  - Arab-Israeli Programs (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 11)
  - Area Studies (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 12)
  - Conflict Resolution (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 13)
  - Constituency Building (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 14)
  - Corporate Involvement (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 15)
  - Cultural Dynamics of Social Change (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 16)
  - Environment and Development (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 17)
  - Gender (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 18)
  - Governance in South Africa (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 19)
  - Higher Education - South Africa (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 20)
  - History of Foundation (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 21)
  - Housing in South Africa (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 25)
  - Human Rights (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 26)
  - Initiatives (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 27)
  - Initiative in International Economics (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 28)
  - International Economic Development (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 29)
  - Media (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 30)
  - Report - Story Ideas (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 31)
  - Reproductive Health (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 32)
  - Southern African Universities (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 33)
  - Sustainable Development (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 34)
  - US Investment In Africa (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 35)
  - Violence (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 36)
  - Women in Agriculture In Africa (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 37)
  - Women and the Law (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 38)
  - Workshop on Local Government (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 39)
  - Youth Development (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 40)
  - Post-Board Luncheon, 1996 June 20 (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 41)
  - Amoako Luncheon, 1996 June 7 (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 42)
  - AME Dinner, 1996 May 20 (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 43)
  - Capacity Building & Communication in Africa, 1996 March 27 (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 44)
  - AME Dinner, 1996 May 20 (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 45)
  - Capacity Building & Communications in Africa, 1996 March 27 (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 46)
  - AME Retreat, 1996 February 16 (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 47)
  - Derek Hanekom, 1995 August 22 (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 48)
  - African-American Summit, 1995 May 4 - 6 (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 49)
  - Biennial Program Review, 1995 March 27 - April 7 (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 50)
  - World Summit for Social Development, 1995 March 27 - April 7 (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 51)
  - ACCORD meeting, 1995 March 20 - 22 (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 52)
  - Worldwide Culture Meeting, 1995 January 15 - 20 (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 53)
  - Investing in Business - The White House, 1994 June 25 - 27 (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 54)
  - South Africa Free Election, 1994 April 27 (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 55)
  - Cairo/West Bank, 1994 March 26 - April 11 (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 56)
  - Kaiser Family Foundation SA Grantmakers Affinity Group, 1994 February 23 - 24 (Box 4 (SK#38717), Folder 57)
- Meeting Files, Organization Files A-B
  - Africa Regional Meeting, 1994 January 9 - 16 (Box 5 (SK#38718), Folder 1)
  - South Africa Office Opening (Box 5 (SK#38718), Folder 2)
  - DAE Working Group, 1993 October 20 - 24 (Box 5 (SK#38718), Folder 3)
  - Association of African Universities, 1993 October 6 - 7 (Box 5 (SK#38718), Folder 4)
  - Africare - Winrock, 1993 October 1 (Box 5 (SK#38718), Folder 5)
  - DAE Working Group of Higher Education, 1993 September 21 (Box 5 (SK#38718), Folder 6)
  - Worldwide RPR Meeting, 1993 September 7 - 10 (Box 5 (SK#38718), Folder 7)
  - UN World Conference on Human Rights, 1993 June 14 - 25 (Box 5 (SK#38718), Folder 8)
  - African-American Conference, 1993 May 19 - 21 (Box 5 (SK#38718), Folder 9)
  - Harvard Institute of International Development, 1993 April 23 (Box 5 (SK#38718), Folder 10)
  - Regional Africa Program Reviews South Africa, 1993 February (Box 5 (SK#38718), Folder 11)
  - ACCORD (Box 5 (SK#38718), Folder 12)
  - The Africa Fund (Box 5 (SK#38718), Folder 13)
  - Africa, 1995 (Box 5 (SK#38718), Folder 14)
  - The African Academy of Sciences (Box 5 (SK#38718), Folder 15)
  - African-American Institute (Box 5 (SK#38718), Folder 16)
  - African Business Round Table (Box 5 (SK#38718), Folder 17)
  - African Development Bank (Box 5 (SK#38718), Folder 18)
  - African Development Foundation (Box 5 (SK#38718), Folder 19)